An X-traordinary origin story.
Pearl is a horror, thriller film directed by Ti West.
Trapped on her family’s isolated farm, Pearl must tend to her ailing father
under the bitter and overbearing watch of her devout mother.
Lusting for a glamorous life like she’s seen in the movies, Pearl’s
ambitions, temptations, and repressions collide.
Pearl, played by Mia Goth.
Projectionist, played by David Corenswet.
Ruth, played by Tandi Wright.
Father, played by Matthew Sunderland.
Mitsy, played by Emma Jenkins-Purro.
Howard, played by Alistair Sewell.
Pearl is a 2022 American psychological horror film directed, produced, and
edited by Ti West, who co-wrote the screenplay with Mia Goth.
It is the second installment in West's X film series and a prequel to X (2022).
Goth reprises her role as the title character, with a supporting cast featuring David
Corenswet, Tandi Wright, Matthew Sunderland, and Emma Jenkins-Purro.
The film serves as an origin story for the titular villain, whose fervent aspiration to become a movie star clashes with
her home life and violent tendencies, leading to violent acts on her family's Texas homestead in 1918.
West began co-writing a prequel script stemming from his
collaboration with Goth while filming X.
Motivated by the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on cinema, filming started in New Zealand immediately after the
first film, using X sets and the Avatar: The Way of Water crew and taking pandemic safety precautions.
Pearl drew inspiration from the works of Douglas Sirk, Technicolor films like The
Wizard of Oz (1939) and Mary Poppins (1964), and Disney films.
It had its world premiere at the 79th Venice International Film Festival on September 3, 2022,
and was released in theaters in the United States on September 16, 2022, by A24.
The film grossed over $10 million and received positive reviews from critics.
MaXXXine, a third film in the series and a direct
sequel to X, was released on July 5, 2024.
Goth reprised her other role from the first film.
The film explores themes of farm, pornography,
dance performance, confession, texas.
The tone is lighthearted and dark and intense.